Soobesükütsa tüa
pia mupitsl ikÜ kimai.
A long time ago. it is said.
a monster came here.
A white tail.
Sarii.
Mahoinitü.
I remember when
Father told me I was ready for kühtaamia.
My big hunt.
You were little.
So. Mother took you to gather medicine.
But Father and I.
we went up into the hills.
The rain was bad. Everything was wet.
We crawled through the mud
and my bowstring…
…got ruined and...
You were sleeping.
I was waiting for it to circle back.
Now you're gonna have to
cross the river to get it.
Whoa.
Don't get your bowstring wet.
Ta a be.
this morning in the sky.
I saw a sign. The thunder bird.
I've been practicing.
It's time. I'm ready for my kühtaamia.
You really think you're ready?
You wanna hunt something
that's hunting you?
Petsü.
- Trained him well.
- It's easy. He's smart.
Not every smart creature is easy to train.
- Is that for War Chief's bad knee?
- Mmm.
He's getting worse.
You didn't put orange totsiyaa.
Who taught you about orange totsiyaa?
You.
Hmm.
Your father left you that
to cut bread root with.
I almost got a deer with it.
Yeah. Well. we can't eat "almost."
My girl. you are good
at so many other things.
Why do you want to hunt?
Because you all think that I can't.
Ah!
In this wind. he brings home a red-tail.
You should have listened to my story.
Didn't think we had time for a nap.
Posa.
It's sharp enough.
Go get us some orange totsiyaa.
It see.
- Hina?
- A lion. It took Puhi.
We gotta find him.
You could get shot sneaking up like that.
Who's sneaking?
Who invited you?
We won't be gone long enough
to need a cook.
She should stay.
She tracks well.
And if we find Puhi alive.
she knows medicine.
You have to find that cat now.
- I will.
- I know.
'Cause you have to.
Oh. good. The dog found shit.
- We're not looking for wolves.
- It's not wolf.
You see that crushed bone?
That's lion scat.
And the cat that made it was big.
He's breathing.
Petsü.
So much could kill him.
It won't kill him.
Just cool his blood.
Anaa. Anaa.
Ta a be wants to stay and hunt.
Let's go.
- I'm coming with you.
- I can handle the lion.
No. it's not just the lion.
Why is Puhi alive? There's something
that scared the cat away from its den.
I've got this.
Stay with Puhi. He needs your help too.
We don't have time to waste talking.
We need to get him home.
ManamÜsohi.
Üts'tü nü.
Tobo'ihupitü.
Kee.
The cold is good.
The medicine slows his blood.
If he gets warm. he'll bleed out.
Hey.
Do you want him
to be comfortable or alive?
Mia.
We don't have time to wait for you.
- Look.
- Could be bear tracks.
Maybe.
But that's a big bear.
And why was it on its hind legs?
And what skins a snake like that?
- We need to keep moving.
- No.
I have to warn my brother.
Paaka. go with her.
Naru. we don't need the torches.
They'll scare the cat.
We're in its hunting grounds.
Why'd you come back?
I found tracks. and they were huge.
I'm not frightened by a bear.
I don't think it was a bear.
I don't know what it was.
I've never seen anything like it.
It skinned and gutted a snake.
Well. whatever it was.
we're in the cat's den now.
We have to deal with it first.
Come on.
The lion won't think
that we're hunting it here.
It'll think it's hunting us.
We get some bait.
then climb up and wait for it.
A hunter doesn't wait. He hunts.
We could be here all night.
We could stalk the forest all night
and not find anything too.
If you're too afraid to hunt.
go back to camp where you belong.
We'll try it Naru's way.
We'll bait it.
then I'll lead the cat to you.
Wait.
It's time. Naru.
Your kühtaamia.
When the lion comes. you tell that thing.
"This is as far as you go.
No more. This is it."
It won't matter how sharp it is
if you're too afraid to use it.
You think you're ready?
You've never faced a lion.
Its mouth full of teeth like arrows.
ready to tear your flesh
and crush your bones.
When your brother comes back.
he and I will find the lion
and kill it.
Your brother carried you home.
Wha... What about the lion?
- Ta a be went after it.
- Okay.
I have to find him.
No. you need to rest.
Ihka.
Drink this tea.
Puhi survived
because of your medicine.
There's something else out there.
Ta a be needs my help.
If your brother needed you.
he wouldn't have brought you back here.
You think the reason for kühtaamia
is to prove you can hunt.
but there's only one reason.
To survive.
Ta a be kima! Ta a be kima!
- Naru.
- War Chief.
Naru.
Where are you going?
We did it.
No.
We didn't do it.
What do you think left those tracks
and skinned that snake?
And before I fell.
- I saw lightning in the trees.
- Naru.
- There's something else out there.
- And if there is. I'll get it.
We need to go back out.
- Far. beyond the ridge line.
- No.
- Okay. Well. I'll hunt alone if I have to.
- You can't.
- Do I need your permission. War Chief?
- It's not about permission.
You can't.
I had to carry you back.
I can hunt.
You're right.
We didn't do it.
I did.
You tried it. You just…
You couldn't bring it home.
If they don't see.
then show them.
Kima.
Next time. you're cooking.
Nüma'ai kima.
We have to go find
whatever left those tracks.
Ühkitsi.
Tasiwoo Atsabi. yütsü tsaaku.
Ürako taa ahpü yühmuku.
Sarii?
There you are.
- What are you doing here?
- Looking for you.
Your brother sent us to bring you home.
Where is he?
Searching for you
on the other side of the pass.
Where are you going?
- I saw it.
- Saw what?
I saw what left those tracks.
- The bear?
- There was a bear.
but there was something else.
and it was huge.
I couldn't see it until it was
covered in blood. but it looked like...
Like a mupitsl.
You saw a monster from a children's story?
It fought and killed a bear
with its hands. easily.
How come it didn't kill you?
Stop!
You're going home.
Enough!
Aitü.
You wanna leave? Then leave.
We're going home.
There's something out there.
Quit it!
Just sit.
You need a leash for your weapon?
Get some water.
We'll rest a minute. Stay together.
- What about Ta a be?
- He'll meet us back at camp.
I said stay together.
I gotta go take a squat.
You want me to do it here?
Water.
You should see your face.
What do you think
drove the possums our way?
Hey. Cut me loose.
Stay down.
Shh.
We have him.
No. He has us.
Look here..
A woman?
What is she doing here?
I'll take her with me..
She is going to slow us down..
No. Judging by how she was running.
I'm sure she saw it.
She's your new blonde. huh?
Get rid of that fucking dog!
Sarii?
I have a bad feeling about this..
You killed the buffalo.
Ah…
You angry?
Now you're going to pay..
Let's see what she knows..
- Talk. dirty Raphael.
- What are you doing here. huh?
- Is this a trap?
- What is going on?
What did you see?
I speak a lot of languages.
You are Comanche. yes?
- I'm going to kill her..
- No. no. no. no no. no. no..
We can still use her..
Ah.
You should be helping us.
I think this creature is a hunter.
looking for the strongest beast.
What do you know?
It killed your whole party.
I'll make her sing..
No.
It didn't kill everyone.
If you were smart. you'd help us.
Get the savage out.
Get him out of the damn cage!
What?
One way or another.
you are going to help us..
Make him bleed!.
Are you hurt?
Oh. they tried.
We shouldn't have brought the horses..
Shut them up or the beast won't show..
Son of a bitch.
The thing the white men
are trying to catch…
…that's what you went out after?
It's what you were tracking?
Yes.
And that's what you chose for kühtaamia?
Where is this fucking beast?
I'm hungry and I have to take a leak..
What is happening?
Oh. no. no. no.
What is going on?
- What is going on?
- What is going on? Rambert!
Shoot. Rambert!
Shit.
I need to get me a horse.
It's here!
- It's coming.
- It's here!
Orü posa kwitapÜ.
Naru.
Can you get your side loose?
We're the bait. He's coming for us.
No.
No. It doesn't want bait.
It doesn't hunt that way.
Before the trappers captured me.
it saw me.
It came right up to me
and then left.
It didn't think I was a threat.
You wanna know how I killed that lion?
Your plan. The tree.
You weakened it.
You had it. Naru.
You can see what I miss.
You always have.
I don't know that this thing
can be killed.
If it bleeds. we can kill it.
Now!
Naru.
Naru!
We got it!
Bastard!
What are you doing?
I have a plan. Get down.
Do you remember the flood
when we were young?
I saw a beaver that had its legs
pinned between two rocks.
The water was rising so fast.
it knew it was going to die.
So it chewed off its own leg.
Fire!
We are going to hit the others!
It was worth it to the beaver…
Wait.
…losing its leg to be free.
Wait. Naru.
What are you doing. Naru? Naru. stop!
I'm smarter than a beaver.
Come on. we gotta go.
- Where are you going?
- I gotta go get us those horses.
I'll get Sarii.
Run! Run!
Hurry up!.
I need help..
We can't do anything for them.
We just have to keep moving.
And the dog?
I like dog..
It tastes better than beaver..
Sarii.
Owehkimia. Ta a be.
Go!
Help me! Help.
You have medicine?
Help me. and I'll show you how to use it.
Please.
Take the powder
and put it in the gun.
Not too little. not too much.
And then what?
Then you take the ball and the cloth.
Put it in the gun.
After that. take the stick you see there.
You put in the gun. uh. three. four times.
Here.
Last thing.
It's okay.
Put powder here.
Then pull that back and it will fire.
That's all?
Please. It hurts.
Please.
What is it?
What's happening? I'm freezing cold.
Please.
Don't leave me.
It can't see him.
Hey!
"Not too much. not too little."
Isa'ai!
We should go.
Ta a be.
Run. Naru.
It thinks I'm the threat.
This is as far as I go.
No more. This is it.
- No.
- Bring it home.
No! Ah. no! No. stop!
Bitch!
You bled my brother.
So now you bleed.
Stupid savage!
You think that I am not a hunter like you.
You're not even aware of
the mistake you just made..
That I am not a threat.
I'm going to put
a bullet in your skull.
That is what makes me dangerous.
You are going to die. bitch!
You can't see that I'm killing you.
And it won't either.
Demon!
No!
Petsü!
Come on. come on. come on. come on.
Do it.
Come on. do it.
This is as far as you go.
No more.
This is it.
Naru iku kima!
Arüka ikÜ! Arüka. Naru kima.
Naru kima.
Hina ma yaa?
There is danger nearby.
We need to move
to easier protected ground.